Guide to the Iron City Legal Assistance Workers Records, 1976-1993 AIS.1984.18
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Iron City Legal Assistance Workers Records
1976-1993
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Iron City Legal Assistance Workers (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1984.18
7.5 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The Iron City Legal Assistance Workers (ICLAW) union was formed in 1981 and represented workers of Neighborhood Legal Services Association, Inc. This collection includes information regarding the formation and activities of ICLAW in western Pennsylvania.
History
The Iron City Legal Assistance Workers (ICLAW) union was formed in 1981 out of the Legal Staff Services Association. ICLAW was chosen to represent workers of the Neighborhood Legal Services Association, Inc. (NLSA) through a National Labor Relations Board election in 1981 and gained affiliation with the National Organization of Legal Service Workers, District 65, United Auto Workers in 1982. The union promoted the availability of legal services and education to low income residents of Allegheny, Beaver, Butler, and Lawrence Counties in Pennsylvania by negotiating fair working conditions, wages and hours in contracts for its members working in the NLSA.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains documents regarding the formation of the Iron City Legal Assistance Workers (ICLAW) union, including organizing committee records, draft by-laws, and National Labor Relations Board election information. Also present are files on contact negotiations between ICLAW and Neighborhood Legal Services Association, Inc. (NLSA). Information regarding ICLAW's political action and advocacy initiatives, in addition to research subject files, are also included.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Precursor Organization, Legal Staff Services Association, 1977-1981
Series II. The Organization of the Iron City Legal Assistance Workers, 1980-1983
Series III. Negotiations, 1981-1988
Series IV. Disputes with Management, 1981-1986
Series V. National Labor Relations Board, 1982-1992
Series VI. Political Action, Lobbying, Advocacy, 1980-1990
Series VII. "Save Legal Services" Campaign, 1981-1984
Series VIII. IC Light ICLAW newsletter, 1982-1984
Series IX. Research and Information Files, 1976-1993
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Iron City Legal Assistance Workers Executive Board on July 11, 1984.
Previous Citation
Iron City Legal Assistance Workers Records, 1976-1993, AIS.1984.18, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Iron City Legal Assistance Workers (I.C.L.A.W.), UE/Labor 84:18, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Legal assistance to the poor -- Pennsylvania -- Pitttsburgh; Legal services -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Labor unions -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Attorney and client -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Labor; Iron City Legal Assistance Workers (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Precursor Organization, Legal Staff Services Association, 1977-1981; I.
  - Legal Staff Services Association, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Regional contracts for Legal Staff Services Associations, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Organization of the Iron City Legal Assistance Workers, 1980-1983; II.
  - NLRB Election, September 11, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Organizing Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Affiliation Agreement with UAW District 65, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bylaws, Staff Surveys, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Draft of contract, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Neighborhood Legal Services Association Proposed Contract, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ICLAW Incomplete Draft of Preamble, Contract Articles, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Negotiations, 1981-1988; III.
  - Negotiating Committee Meeting Notes and Memoranda, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Requests for NLSA Financial Projections and Management Letters to Staff, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Negotiating Committee Notes and NLSA Funding, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Draft of Contract and Negotiating Committee Notes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Memoranda, and NLSA Financial Projections, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Requests for NLSA Financial Projections and NLSA Letters to Staff, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Proposals/Counterproposals, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - NLSA Financial Projections, Memoranda, and Financial Worksheets, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hubbard Interim Agreement and Modification of Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Contract Proposals/Counterproposals, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Memoranda of agreement, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda of agreement, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NLSA Memoranda and Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Drafts of Contracts and Proposals, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Negotiating Committee Notes and Memoranda, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Disputes with Management, 1981-1986; IV.
  - "Trainergate": South East Asian Training Conference, Pittsburgh, January 30-31, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Trainergate": Budget and Financial, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Trainergate": Union Research, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Voluntary Layoffs Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Voluntary Layoffs Financial Information, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Employee Suspensions and Transfers, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Legal Aid Society and United Way, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- National Labor Relations Board, 1982-1992; V.
  - Back Pay Issue, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Payment of Agency Dues by Non-Union Members, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Removal of Litigation Unit Counselor from Bargaining Unit, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - Alleged Unilateral Changes in Terms and Condition of Employment, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Separation of NLSA and Legal Aid Society, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Political Action, Lobbying, and Advocacy, 1980-1990; VI.
  - NLSA, Newspaper Clippings, Memoranda, and Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National Organization of Legal Service Workers, Union Literature, and Briefings, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ICLAW Correspondence and Memoranda, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Union Members' Pension Information and Pay Plans, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Notes, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda, Minutes, and Agendas, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Acknowledgments of Support, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings RE: NLSA staff layoffs, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Notes on Preventing "Legal Service Layoffs", 1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Advocacy for Increased Staff Funding for Legal Services, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notes on NLSA Financial Projections, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lobbying at National Legal Service Corporation Board Meeting, December 1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lobbying at National Legal Service Corporation Board Meeting, December 1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 10% Program, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Challenge to NLSA Employment of Baskin and Sears, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Participation in NLSA Budget Talks, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- "Save Legal Service" Campaign, 1981-1984; VII.
  - Project Advisory Group: Legislative Updates, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Coalition for Legal Services, Correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Legal Services Corporation, Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - NLSA Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- IC Light, ICLAW Newsletter, 1982-1984; VIII.
  - IC Light, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Research and Information Files, 1976-1993; IX.
  - Distributive Worker, UAW District 65, New York City (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - ICLAW Fact Sheet (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Law Journal Articles, Legal Services, 1980-1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Political Rights Defense Fund" Newsletter by Political Rights Defense Fun, New York City, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Beaver County, PA Organizing Drive, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Contracts for Other Legal Service Workers and Locals, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Contracts for Other Legal Service Workers and Locals, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Illinois Court Case: Eligible Residents of Austin Garfield v. Legal Assistance Foundation, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Oregon Court Case: Release of Personnel Services Files to Legal Services Corporation, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 13-18)
  - Labor Literature: Political Actions Alerts and Letters, 1979-1988 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Labor Literature: Pamphlets and Brochures, 1980-1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Layoffs in National Legal Services, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Legal Services Corporation Annual Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Articles on Federal Inquiry in Mismanagement of Legal Services Corporation, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Legal Services Corporation and National Organization of Legal Service Workers, National Negotiations, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - NLSA Financial Information Staff Notes, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - NLSA Financial Information, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - NLSA Financial Information, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - NLSA Management, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - NLSA Memos to Staff, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - NLSA Miscellaneous, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - NLSA Personnel Committee Meeting Notices, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - NLSA Personnel Policies, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - NLSA Staff Notes, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - NLSA Voluntary Layoffs and Financial Information, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - National Organization of Legal Service Workers (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - NOLSW Constitution, By-Laws, and Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Pittsburgh Legal Aid Society, 1983-1992 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - UAW-NOLSW Correspondence, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 21-23)
  - UAW Stewards Kit from NOLSW National Convention, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - NOLSW Convention, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - NOLSW Fight Back Program, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - NOLSW Memoranda, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - NOLSW National Convention, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - NOLSW National Executive Committee Meeting, June 24-26, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - National UAW-CAP Conference, Washington D.C., 1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)